<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/" xmlns:webfeeds="http://webfeeds.org/rss/1.0" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Spiritus Ranae</title>
    <link>https://www.atoms.net/blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://www.atoms.net/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <description>Lume Simple Blog variant</description>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 17:37:29 GMT</lastBuildDate>
    <language>en</language>
    <generator>Lume 3.1.2</generator>
    <item>
      <title>Robot Minimum Wage</title>
      <link>https://www.atoms.net/blog/robot1/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.atoms.net/blog/robot1/</guid>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<p>and the robots have to give all their wages, initially to the unemployed and underemployed and then eventually, when all the non-automated jobs are gone, to everyone.</p>
<p>Put another way: robots are paid a wage somewhat comparable to the wage that would have been paid to a human worker. Those wages are taxed at 100%. That tax income is then used to fund unemployment payments, and over time, gradually shifted over to pay for a universal basic income.</p>
]]>
      </content:encoded>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Added some Logging</title>
      <link>https://www.atoms.net/blog/loggy/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.atoms.net/blog/loggy/</guid>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<p>I just added a tiny, privacy‑friendly “pageview counter” to this blog that runs for free, doesn’t use Google Analytics, and avoids collecting personal data.
​</p>
<h2 id="what-problem-this-solves" tabindex="-1"><a href="https://www.atoms.net/blog/loggy/#what-problem-this-solves" class="header-anchor">What problem this solves</a></h2>
<p>Most analytics tools track a lot more than many small sites need: they set cookies, profile visitors, and phone home to big platforms just to answer basic questions like “Which pages are people reading?” and “Is anyone visiting this thing?” The goal here was different: count visits and see which pages get attention, without building dossiers on readers or depending on gross ad‑tech companies.
​</p>
<h2 id="what-i-built-instead" tabindex="-1"><a href="https://www.atoms.net/blog/loggy/#what-i-built-instead" class="header-anchor">What I built instead</a></h2>
<p>A tiny web service (hosted on <a href="https://deno.com/deploy">Deno Deploy</a>) that receives a simple “someone/something viewed this page” message whenever a page on the site loads.
​</p>
<p>The service is a very small snippet of JavaScript added to the blog’s template that sends just three pieces of information:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p>Which page was viewed (the URL path)</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The page title</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Where the visitor came from on the site (the referrer)</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>The service does not store IP addresses, cookies, or unique identifiers—only high‑level information that’s useful for understanding traffic, not tracking people.
​</p>
<h2 id="how-it-works-behind-the-scenes" tabindex="-1"><a href="https://www.atoms.net/blog/loggy/#how-it-works-behind-the-scenes" class="header-anchor">How it works behind the scenes</a></h2>
<p>When someone opens a page on the site, their browser quietly makes a background request to the analytics service saying “Page /blog/archive/ was viewed.” The service checks that the request comes from a web page, updates an in‑memory counter for that page, and writes a brief log line (timestamp, path, title, referrer, and browser type).
​</p>
<h2 id="what-makes-it-privacy%E2%80%91respecting" tabindex="-1"><a href="https://www.atoms.net/blog/loggy/#what-makes-it-privacy%E2%80%91respecting" class="header-anchor">What makes it privacy‑respecting</a></h2>
<p>No cookies and no fingerprinting. The system doesn’t try to recognize or follow a person across visits; it only counts pageviews.
​</p>
<h3 id="minimal-data" tabindex="-1"><a href="https://www.atoms.net/blog/loggy/#minimal-data" class="header-anchor">Minimal data</a></h3>
<p>It records just enough to answer “what is being read?” rather than “who is reading it?”.
​</p>
<h2 id="why-this-is-a-good-fit-for-a-personal-blog" tabindex="-1"><a href="https://www.atoms.net/blog/loggy/#why-this-is-a-good-fit-for-a-personal-blog" class="header-anchor">Why this is a good fit for a personal blog</a></h2>
<p>For a small site or personal blog with no commericial interests whatsoever, the interesting questions are about content, not people: which posts resonate, which pages nobody sees, and whether the site is still alive in the eyes of readers. This setup answers those questions with a tiny, understandable, and host‑agnostic piece of plumbing - no dashboards, no trackers, and no dependence on ad‑network analytics.
​</p>
]]>
      </content:encoded>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Counter-Protest is Gote (後手)</title>
      <link>https://www.atoms.net/blog/sente/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.atoms.net/blog/sente/</guid>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<p>The Japanese term, <em>sente</em> (先手) means &quot;prior hand&quot; or &quot;first move&quot;. In the game of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Go_(game)">Go</a>, sente translates roughly into the english term &quot;initiative&quot;.</p>
<p>I've been spending a couple/few hours on most recent Monday evenings counter-protesting at our Alderwoman's office on Archer Avenue in Chicago. A very small, but obnoxiously loud group of <em>people</em> have been <a href="https://chi.streetsblog.org/2025/12/10/whats-the-future-of-archer-safe-streets-advocates-faced-off-against-car-activists-backed-by-pro-charter-school-lobbying-group-urban-center">stiring up opposition to a traffic safety project</a> on Archer which was approved after years of public meetings at which there was approximately zero opposition. The scheduling just happens to co-incide with &quot;Ward Night&quot; - the time when the ward staff and the alderwoman makes themselves available for walk-in visits from constituents (actually one can visit any time they are open). The loudest of the dozen or so regular protesters are afflilated with conservative groups opposed to our progressive alder. Their motives are suspect to say the least.</p>
<p>For reasons unrelated to the Archer Avenue astroturfing, I'm exhausted with participating in public protests, so I'm not objective. But I'd really rather spend my winter Monday evenings doing almost anything other than standing around in the cold showing support for the safety project by holding signs and quite possibly being mistaken for a protester, rather than a counter-protester by a subset(?) of the passing drivers who can be bothered to pay any attention at all to the situation.</p>
<p>At last night's counter-protest I was reminded of Go's concept of sente. It is a bit of an exaggeration, but I've heard it said that to lose sente - to lose intitiative - is to lose the game. After one has lost initiative, one's move is reactive and worse, there may only be one weak, defensive move to make and if that isn't bad enough, that move is dictated by one's opponent. The pain! To counter-protest is to react - in Go terms, this state of reacting to an opponent who has seized the initiative is called <em>gote</em> (後手) - literally, &quot;after hand&quot;. There is a way out of the situation in Go called <em>tenuki</em> (手抜き) in which a player who has lost the initiative intentionally ignores the threat and instead of defending, makes a move elsewhere. I wonder if it may be time for tenuki on Archer?</p>
]]>
      </content:encoded>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Public Sans</title>
      <link>https://www.atoms.net/blog/public-sans/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.atoms.net/blog/public-sans/</guid>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<p>Our tax dollars are making this awesome new typeface,  <a href="https://public-sans.digital.gov/">Public Sans</a>  available for free. Please, no one tell <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/rubio-orders-state-department-change-official-memo-font/story?id=128282010"> Secretary of State Marco Rubio</a> about this!</p>
<p>For more background on the absurd Rubio tantrum see: <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/12/09/us/politics/rubio-state-department-font.html">this NYT article</a></p>
]]>
      </content:encoded>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Caving By Any Other Name</title>
      <link>https://www.atoms.net/blog/northwestern/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.atoms.net/blog/northwestern/</guid>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<h2 id="disappointed-with-northwestern" tabindex="-1"><a href="https://www.atoms.net/blog/northwestern/#disappointed-with-northwestern" class="header-anchor">Disappointed with Northwestern</a></h2>
<p>Early on, when the trump adminstration was coercing colleges into toeing the MAGA line, it looked like  universities <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2025/10/16/us/trump-universities-compact-funding">might resist</a>. I could not be more disappointed to see that <a href="https://chicago.suntimes.com/education/2025/12/02/northwestern-trump-settlement-deering-meadow-freeze-federal-funding-dei-transgender-admissions-antisemitism">Northwestern caved</a> into trump's demands AND had the temerity to claim that it was preserving its independence while doing so.</p>
<p>Northwestern's $14.3 billion endowment could have been prudently used to cover some or all of the federal funding the government threatened to withhold.</p>
<h2 id="forgiveness" tabindex="-1"><a href="https://www.atoms.net/blog/northwestern/#forgiveness" class="header-anchor">Forgiveness</a></h2>
<p>In this excellent post on <a href="https://marienewman.substack.com/p/why-forgiving-not-forgetting-marjorie">Why Forgiving (Not Forgetting) Marjorie Taylor Greene May Make Sense for America (and Me)</a>
Marie Newman reiterates the concept that Forgiveness is for you, it is not for the offending party. Newman did not originate the concept, but somehow I hadn't heard it before (or forgot if I did) so she gets the credit. There are of course, differing schools of thought about this view of forgiveness, but it makes sense to me, at least in context of MTG or, Northwestern University for cravenly capitulating to the trump adminstrations demands to give up its independence and pay a huge fine in order to preserve some federal funding.</p>
<p><strong>Some more thoughts, in no particular order added Dec 30, 2025</strong></p>
<p>Northwestern could look at this example of how to stand up to a bully who is threatening to stop federal funding:
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Katherine_Maher">NPR's CEO Katherine_Maher's wikipedia entry</a></p>
<h2 id="is-it-too-late%3F" tabindex="-1"><a href="https://www.atoms.net/blog/northwestern/#is-it-too-late%3F" class="header-anchor">Is it too late?</a></h2>
<p>Northwestern can draw from its own history of breaking agreements if it believes it's too late to assert independence.</p>
<p>If it can dissolve the <a href="https://dailynorthwestern.com/2024/04/29/campus/breaking-administrators-student-demonstrators-reach-agreement-to-end-encampment/">Deering Meadow Agreement</a>, it can also back out of its capitulation to trump. Then again, it might have to acknowledge <a href="https://dailynorthwestern.com/2025/11/30/campus/northwestern-takes-down-online-information-about-deering-meadow-agreement/">the existence of the Deering Meadow Agreement</a> in order to reinstate it.</p>
<p>For now, I'm not yet burning my Northwestern Wildcats hoodie, but I'm also no longer wearing it in public.</p>
<p>Also see:
<a href="https://dailynorthwestern.com/2025/12/21/campus/pritzker-professors-question-legality-of-northwestern-funding-deal-with-trump-administration/">Pritzker professors question legality of Northwestern funding deal</a></p>
]]>
      </content:encoded>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can We Have Nice Things?</title>
      <link>https://www.atoms.net/blog/makearchergreatagain/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.atoms.net/blog/makearchergreatagain/</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://www.atoms.net/uploads/maga.png" alt="Image"></p>
]]></content:encoded>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why and How a Blog Now?</title>
      <link>https://www.atoms.net/blog/instructions/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.atoms.net/blog/instructions/</guid>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<p>Good questions!</p>
<!--more-->
<h2 id="why%3F" tabindex="-1"><a href="https://www.atoms.net/blog/instructions/#why%3F" class="header-anchor">Why?</a></h2>
<p>Like everyone, I have some things to say. Unlike everyone, I'm mostly refusing to use social media, and since I'm not hugely into speaking with actual people in the so called real world, this seems like a viable option. (In other words this is a slightly less and slightly more crazy person technique for expressing the inner dialog.) ALSO there will be some pretty tedious notes to myself of a more practical nature - like WHEN did I last acquire our last ever non-stick pan? (this time I mean it!)</p>
<div class="markdown-alert markdown-alert-tip">
<p class="markdown-alert-title">Tip</p>
<p>I'm using some features of the theme and blogging software here, like this tip, which isn't really a tip at all, mostly so I remember that they exist and have an example of how to use them laying around.</p>
</div>
<h2 id="how%3F" tabindex="-1"><a href="https://www.atoms.net/blog/instructions/#how%3F" class="header-anchor">How?</a></h2>
<p>The blog software <a href="https://lume.land/">Lume</a> runs in
<a href="https://deno.com/">Deno</a>, using the pretty awesome <a href="https://lume.land/theme/xeo/">Xeo theme</a></p>
<div class="markdown-alert markdown-alert-note">
<p class="markdown-alert-title">Note</p>
<p>Like the tip that isn't a tip, this note is well, I guess it actually is a note. So never mind.</p>
</div>
<h2 id="what's-with-the-frog-and-the-pretentious-title%3F" tabindex="-1"><a href="https://www.atoms.net/blog/instructions/#what's-with-the-frog-and-the-pretentious-title%3F" class="header-anchor">What's with the frog and the pretentious title?</a></h2>
<p>Some obsessions may be revealed, such as my obsession with <a href="https://www.britannica.com/science/How-Do-Frogs-Breathe">Frog Respiration</a>. Other obsessions, such as riding the <a href="https://www.onepeloton.com/">Peloton &quot;bike&quot;</a> will be lurking under the surface, almost in secret, until I run out of other things to prattle on about.
Spiritus Ranae, is sort-of Latin, or perhaps actual Latin for &quot;Breath of the Frog&quot;. For about four years, my Peloton user-name was &quot;Frog Breath&quot;. There was some non-happiness about it from people I love and/or respect, so I eventually changed it to &quot;Spiritus Ranae&quot; about which I have as yet heard no compliants. (Then again, an eye roll is silent!)</p>
<h2 id="wut%3F" tabindex="-1"><a href="https://www.atoms.net/blog/instructions/#wut%3F" class="header-anchor">Wut?</a></h2>
<p>A few broad topics and particular ideas I might eventually get around to yammering about:</p>
<h3 id="a-fantasy-letter-to-the-president" tabindex="-1"><a href="https://www.atoms.net/blog/instructions/#a-fantasy-letter-to-the-president" class="header-anchor">A Fantasy Letter to the President</a></h3>
<p>I had this idea - entirely driven by magical thinking - that one could write a letter to our depraved president which could turn him around, make him see how cruel and counterproductive his whole schtick is and even get him to unbreak our hearts by fixing the enormous mess he's created.</p>
<p>Could this actually work? Probably not. But should that keep us from writing such a letter?</p>
<h3 id="northwestern-caved-and-pretended-not-to-cave" tabindex="-1"><a href="https://www.atoms.net/blog/instructions/#northwestern-caved-and-pretended-not-to-cave" class="header-anchor">Northwestern Caved and Pretended not to Cave</a></h3>
<p>$75M but no admission of wrongdoing... so wrong!</p>
<h3 id="back-when-i-had-gills" tabindex="-1"><a href="https://www.atoms.net/blog/instructions/#back-when-i-had-gills" class="header-anchor">Back When I Had Gills</a></h3>
<p>There will be song titles for songs that may or may not ever get written.</p>
<h3 id="always-be-crafting!" tabindex="-1"><a href="https://www.atoms.net/blog/instructions/#always-be-crafting!" class="header-anchor">Always Be Crafting!</a></h3>
<p>love that section of the <a href="https://wewillcraft.org/#values">We Will Craft</a> values page.</p>
<h3 id="if-ilhan-omar-is-garbage-i-am-100%25-pro-garbage" tabindex="-1"><a href="https://www.atoms.net/blog/instructions/#if-ilhan-omar-is-garbage-i-am-100%25-pro-garbage" class="header-anchor">If Ilhan Omar is Garbage I am 100% Pro-Garbage</a></h3>
<p>asdf</p>
<h3 id="my-crushing-disappointment-with-pantone%E2%80%99s-2026-color-of-the-year" tabindex="-1"><a href="https://www.atoms.net/blog/instructions/#my-crushing-disappointment-with-pantone%E2%80%99s-2026-color-of-the-year" class="header-anchor">My Crushing Disappointment with Pantone’s 2026 Color of the Year</a></h3>
<p>a white? really?</p>
<h3 id="video-game" tabindex="-1"><a href="https://www.atoms.net/blog/instructions/#video-game" class="header-anchor">Video Game</a></h3>
<p><a href="https://www.backmarket.com/en-us/c/tech-education/currensy-sega-genesis-device-that-made-me?lid=jt9j3ftd4tql">Device That Made Me: Curren$y on Sega Genesis</a></p>
<h3 id="how-to-live-in-a-world-of-extreme-beauty%2C-which-is-on-fire-and-brimming-with-injustice%3F" tabindex="-1"><a href="https://www.atoms.net/blog/instructions/#how-to-live-in-a-world-of-extreme-beauty%2C-which-is-on-fire-and-brimming-with-injustice%3F" class="header-anchor">How to Live in a world of extreme beauty, which is on fire and brimming with injustice?</a></h3>
<h2 id="another-heading!" tabindex="-1"><a href="https://www.atoms.net/blog/instructions/#another-heading!" class="header-anchor">Another Heading!</a></h2>
]]>
      </content:encoded>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is This Thing On?</title>
      <link>https://www.atoms.net/blog/differences/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.atoms.net/blog/differences/</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Yes it is a blog!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 16:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>